Puerto Rican Oral History Project records 1976.001
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Ferrell, Julio, 1973 May 10; 1976.001.017
  Ferrell, Julio, 1892-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); DUMBO Historic District (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic identity; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Factories |z New York (State) |z New York; Great Depression |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Festa, Josephine and Tejada, Gloria, 1974 June 23; 1976.001.018
  Josephine Festa and Gloria Tejada, who are siblings and children of Puerto Rican parents, were born and raised in the Brooklyn neighborhood of DUMBO, before moving to Bay Shore in Long Island. Festa and Tejada both attended Public School #5 in Brooklyn, New York. Festa was a former dental assistant before becoming a housewife. Tejada was trained in mental health.
  In this interview, siblings Josephine Festa and Gloria Tejada discuss growing up in the ethnically diverse Brooklyn neighborhood of DUMBO and the surrounding Brooklyn neighborhoods of Downtown Brooklyn and Vinegar Hill. Festa and Tejada discuss the role that the Catholic Church and nuns played on the development of Puerto Rican youths, and describe the duality of attending a public school where ethnic groups often remained to themselves, while also coexisting in an integrated community. Interview conducted by Monte Rivera.
  Bonilla, Carmelita, 1908-; Festa, Josephine, 1927-; New York Naval Shipyard.; Tejada, Gloria, 1925-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); DUMBO Historic District (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |x Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York Region |x Religion; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Vinegar Hill (New York, N.Y.)
- Figueroa, Rosario, 1974 November 12; 1976.001.019
  Rosario Figueroa was born in 1902 in Puerto Rico. She arrived in Brooklyn on October 23, 1936 aboard the steamship Borinquen. A sewing machine operator in clothing factories, she resided in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn for thirty years before moving to Corona, Queens - where she lived at the time of the interview in 1974. As factory worker, wife, mother of two, and grandmother, she managed during both high and low points for industry and prosperity in the United States. Rosario Figueroa died in August, 1989.
  In the interview, Rosario Figueroa recounts her arrival in Brooklyn aboard the S.S. Borinquen in 1936, as well as her experience making ends meet in various Brooklyn factories over several decades. From a cold-water flat on the industrial border between the Williamsburg and Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhoods of Brooklyn to a comfortable home in Corona, Queens, Figueroa discusses her life's journey as a wife, mother, and worker in twentieth century New York - including details about the Great Depression of the 1930s, and the 1940s. Interview in Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Figueroa, Rosario, 1902-; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Factories |z New York (State); Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Rican women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Work environment |z United States
- Fontanez, Santiago Soto, 1974 September 18; 1976.001.020
  Reverend Santiago Soto Fontánez was born in Caguas, Puerto Rico in 1904, and grew up in Ponce, Puerto Rico. Rev. Fontánez received his bachelor's and master's degrees in education at the University of Puerto Rico. He moved to the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1947. He was a professor at Brooklyn College, as well as a Baptist minister. He died in 1985, a few years after writing his autobiography Misión a la Puerta, Mission at the Door.
  In the interview, Reverend Santiago Soto Fontánez reflects on his role as the first Puerto Rican on the local school board in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Williamsburg, describes the figures who supported and helped the Puerto Rican community in Williamsburg, and also describes the limitations he faces as a Baptist Minister in the Puerto Rican community. Rev. Fontánez explains the importance of understanding the religions that Puerto Ricans believe in to help understand their culture. Interview conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Brooklyn College.; Central Baptist Church of Williamsburgh (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; Fontanez, Santiago Soto, 1904-; Universidad de Puerto Rico. Centro de Investigaciones.; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ponce (P.R.); Puerto Rican youth; Puerto Ricans |x Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York Region |x Religion; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Societies, etc.; Puerto Rico; San Juan (P.R); Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.)
- Fortun, Maria, 1974 December 23; 1976.001.021
  Maria Fortún was seventy-five years old in 1974 when she was interviewed. She came to Brooklyn, from Puerto Rico, on December 5, 1923 at the age of twenty-four and lived there permanently. Fortún had attained a fourth grade level education and was retired in 1974.
  In this interview, Maria Fortún discusses the ethnic distribution and social conditions of the Brooklyn neighborhood of Downtown Brooklyn; specifically referring to Columbia Street. She discusses the early political organization "Hijos de Borinquen," and its founder Antonia Denis. Interview in Spanish conducted by Jaime Barreto.
  Denis, Antonia; Fortun, Maria, 1899-; Tapia, Carlos; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Columbia Heights (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Political clubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Rican women |x Political activity |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions |y 20th century
- Garden, Maximina, 1974 January 22; 1976.001.022
  Maximina Garden was born in 1913 in Cabo Rojo, Puerto Rico. She was forced to leave school after second grade in order to care for her widowed mother. Garden's mother died a few year later, when she was ten years old, after which she went to live with relatives. Garden sought a better life in New York, arriving in Brooklyn on the ship El Ponce on December 2, 1939 - and living in various addresses in Downtown Brooklyn and the surrounding Brooklyn neighborhoods of Brooklyn Heights and Fort Greene. After getting married, she worked in a Brooklyn garment factory at 85 Dekalb Avenue for many years.
  In the interview, Maximina Garden recounts her childhood in Puerto Rico, where she sacrificed an education to care for her widowed mother, her trip via the ship El Ponce to Brooklyn and her reasons for migrating to New York. She recalls a time when there were very few Puerto Ricans in Brooklyn, and describes the housing conditions in Downtown Brooklyn - and the surrounding Brooklyn neighborhoods of Brooklyn Heights and Fort Greene - where she resided at a number of locations. Garden also discusses her years at a garment factory at 85 Dekalb Avenue, where her coworkers were predominantly Italian and Jewish. She ends the conversation with details about her life as it stands at the time of the interview in 1974. Interview in Spanish conducted by Pedro Miranda.
  Garden, Maximina, 1913-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Factories |z New York (State); Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Great Depression |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Rican women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Work environment |z United States
- Giboyeaux, Jose Ramon, 1974 October 22; 1976.001.023
  José Ramón Giboyeaux was born in Bayamón, Puerto Rico circa 1904. He was raised by his sister and brother in law in Vega Alta, Puerto Rico and later relocated to Vega Baja to attend high school. Giboyeaux worked at a pineapple farm and sugar mill before attending the University of Puerto Rico to pursue a rural teacher certificate. The narrator was active in workers’ unions in the island before quitting his job and moving to Brooklyn, New York in 1924. Giboyeaux was also active in workers’ unions in New York and was a member of the civic group La Liga Puertorriqueña and founding member of La Civica Vanguardia Puertorriqueña.
  In this interview, José Ramón Giboyeaux reflects on his interaction with several Puerto Rican personalities, political figures, and community leaders in the 1920s and 1930s. He also recalls his involvement in the Young Communist Party in Brooklyn during the 1930s alongside Jesus Colón. Giboyeaux remembers the many political activities in the Puerto Rican community of Brooklyn, such as the establishment of clubs. Interview as Spanish transcript only was conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Colon, Jesus, 1901-1974; Giboyeaux, Jose Ramon, 1901-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic relations; Gangs |z New York (State) |z Kings Country; Political clubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs |y 20th century
- Gonzalez, Carmen Fortun, 1974 December 26; 1976.001.024
  Carmen Fortún González was born in Brooklyn, New York in 1926. Both of González’s parents were Puerto Rican, her father having moved to Brooklyn in 1912 and her mother in 1919. The narrator was exposed to political and social activism at an early time as her father lent his barbershop to community leaders to use as a meeting space. As an adult, she was involved in several Puerto Rican and Latin American civic, political, and educational organizations in Brooklyn. She worked as a stenographer at Borough Hall in Brooklyn and at the newspaper La Prensa. At the time of the 1974 interview, González was employed by the Fort Greene Community Corporation as a human resources specialist.
  In this interview, Carmen Fortún González describes her parents’ reasons for moving to New York from Puerto Rico and their first impressions of the city. She discusses several public figures such as Antonia Denis, Carlos Tapia, and James A. Kelly and their role in the Puerto Rican community in Brooklyn. The narrator also talks about Puerto Rican migration after the 1940s and the current situation of the newest immigrants in comparison to those who moved to Brooklyn before World War II. She also discusses the current state of Puerto Rican organizations in Brooklyn. González expresses her disappointment in Puerto Rican organizations in terms of the lack of interest in working with the community in Brooklyn, instead focusing efforts in Manhattan. Interview in Spanish conducted by Jaime Barreto.
  Denis, Antonia; Gonzalez, Carmen, 1926-; Kelly, James; Tapia, Carlos; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Political clubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Societies, etc.; Puerto Rico; Race relations |z United States; Red Hook (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Guanill, Elizabeth, 1974 June 18; 1976.001.025
  Elizabeth Guanill was born in 1924 to Puerto Rican migrants in the DUMBO neighborhood of Brooklyn. Her family came to Brooklyn in 1915. Guanill's mother was a translator and her father was a cab driver and postal employee who later worked for an aviation company and founded a fruit and grocery market on Long Island. Guanill spent her first ten years in Downtown Brooklyn and the remainder of her youth in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Williamsburg. She married her husband Pedro Guanill, a merchant marine, in 1943. Guanill attended Brooklyn College before moving out to eastern Long Island. At the time of the interview in 1974, Guanill and her husband lived in Bayshore, in Suffolk County, Long Island.
  In this interview, Elizabeth Guanill describes being born to Puerto Rican migrants in Brooklyn. She recalls the social and cultural life, as well as the ethnic distribution of the Downtown and Williamsburg neighborhoods of Brooklyn in which she was raised. She also discusses the differences between Puerto Rican migrants that came to New York in years past and those who came more recently, as well as the role of community leaders such as “Sister Carmelita” (Carmela Zapata Bonilla Marrero) and Carlos Tapia in the Puerto Rican community of New York City. Interview conducted by Monte Rivera.
  Guanill, Elizabeth, 1924-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Rican women; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York Region |x Religion; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.)
- Guanill, Pedro, 1974 June 18; 1976.001.026
  Pedro Guanill was born in 1915 in Puerta de Tierra, Puerto Rico. He migrated to the United States in 1933, at the age of eighteen. Arriving in Brooklyn, he first worked in factories, then as a boxer, and finally as a merchant marine. Guanill resided in numerous New York City neighborhoods - including long periods spent in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn and Downtown Brooklyn. In 1943, he married Elizabeth Guanill, whom he had met in Williamsburg. At the time of the interview in 1974 Guanill and his wife lived in Bayshore, Suffolk County, on eastern Long Island. He died in 1997.
  In the interview, Pedro Guanill talks about his experiences as a factory worker, boxer and merchant seaman during the interwar and World War II period. He also describes the Williamsburg and Downtown neighborhoods of Brooklyn in the 1930s and 1940s. Guanill touches on the life of community leader and businessman Carlos Tapia, as well as the Baldorioty Democratic Club. There are some specific references to Carlos Tapia's restaurant and other Puerto Rican-owned small businesses during that time. Interview conducted by Monte Rivera.
  Guanill, Pedro, 1915-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Factories |z New York (State); Games |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Work environment |z United States
- Hernandez, Julio, 1974 December; 1976.001.027
  Julio Hernández was born in Brooklyn, New York in 1925, and had lived in Brooklyn consistently when he was interviewed in 1974. He served as the Director of both the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) chapter of New York and the Puerto Rican Merchants Association. He also was an advisory board member of the Borough of Northern Manhattan.
  In the interview, Julio Hernández discusses the economic conditions of Puerto Ricans in Brooklyn, New York. He describes the ethnic distribution in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Red Hook. Hernández talks about the political movements by Puerto Ricans in Brooklyn, where he refers to the Betances Democratic Club, and political leaders including Jesus Colón, Antonia Denis, and Louis Weber. Interview in Spanish conducted by Jamie Barreto.
  Betances Club.; Denis, Antonia; Hernandez, Julio, 1925-; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.; Puerto Rican Merchants Association.; Tapia, Carlos; Weber, Louis; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Political clubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Societies, etc.; Puerto Rico; Red Hook (New York, N.Y.)
- Hernandez, Luis, 1974 November 4; 1976.001.028
  Luis Hernández arrived in Brooklyn, New York in 1926 at the age of two or three years old and lived in the borough for at least the next five decades. Coming from a very active, civic-minded family, he had been involved politically in the borough since his early youth. At the time of this 1974 interview, Hernández was the Commissioner of Relocation and Rehabilitation for the city. He also founded the Voter’s Club and was actively involved in the political life of the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn.
  In the interview, Commissioner Luis Hernández discusses the general social conditions of the early Puerto Ricans in Downtown Brooklyn. He briefly surveys the altercations between Italian, Irish, and Puerto Rican gangs. He references the first Puerto Rican Democratic club founded in 1928, the Borinquen Democratic Club and its founders. Commissioner Hernández also shares details on his four brothers in relation to the family’s work ethic and professions. Interview conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Colon, Jesus, 1901-1974; Denis, Antonia; Giboyeaux, Jose Ramon, 1901-; Hernandez, Luis, 1920-; Tapia, Carlos; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Political clubs |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Hostalaza, Emilio, 1974 November 5; 1976.001.029
  Emilio Hostalaza was born in Puerto Rico in 1899 and arrived in Brooklyn, New York, on April 23, 1929. At the time of his interview in 1974, he had lived in Brooklyn for forty-five years. He resided in several Brooklyn neighborhoods, including the Brooklyn neighborhoods of Clinton Hill, Williamsburg, and DUMBO. He was employed in the restaurant business as a cook during his time in Brooklyn.
  In this interview, Emilio Hostalaza discusses political movements within Puerto Rican clubs, where he relates specific information on the beginnings and transformations of the Betances Democratic Club. He describes political leaders in the community, such as Carlos Tapia and Jesus Colón. He describes the ethnic distribution of the Brooklyn neighborhood of Clinton Hill and the economic conditions of the Puerto Rican community. Interview in Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Colon, Jesus, 1901-1974; Hostalaza, Emilio, 1900-; Tapia, Carlos; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Clinton Hill (New York, N.Y.); DUMBO Historic District (New York, N.Y.); Political clubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Societies, etc.; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.)
- Irizarry, Honorina Weber, 1974 October 17; 1976.001.030
  Born in 1902, Honorina Weber Irizarry arrived in Brooklyn in 1928 and remained a resident well into the 1970s. A college graduate, she owned a small business in Brooklyn at the time of this 1974 interview. Married in 1930, she was a grandmother by 1974. Irizarry is also the sister of the well-known Puerto Rican benefactor Louis Weber. She died in 1980.
  Honorina Weber Irizarry relates information on the first Democratic Puerto Rican clubs, and on those involved in their creation. She references Louis Weber and Carlos Tapia, specifically discussing their styles of interacting with the community. She recalls her work history as a multilingual translator in Lower Manhattan. Irizarry also describes the ethnic distribution of the Columbia Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Interview conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Irizarry, Honorina Weber, 1906-; Tapia, Carlos; Weber, Louis; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Columbia Heights (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Political clubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Societies, etc.
- LaRosa, Ramon, 1974 October 30; 1976.001.031
  Ramon LaRosa arrived in Brooklyn in 1917 and stayed there since his arrival. LaRosa had a limited formal education. When he was interviewed in 1974, he was a retired factory worker. He had been employed at the Welder-Brillo Manufacturing Company for over forty-five years and was a merchant seaman for eight years. He died in 1978.
  In the interview, Ramon LaRosa discusses the economic conditions of Puerto Ricans during the 1920s and 1930s. He describes the social conditions of Brooklyn, New York, and he reflects on his personal relationships with Italians on the Brooklyn waterfront. He describes the personalities of political leaders in the Puerto Rican community, including Louis Weber and Carlos Tapia. Interview in Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  LaRosa, Ramon, 1898-; Tapia, Carlos; Weber, Louis; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Clinton Hill (New York, N.Y.); DUMBO Historic District (New York, N.Y.); Factories |z New York (State); Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions |y 20th century
- Larregui, Dick, 1974 September 11; 1976.001.032